<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
  [
    <!ENTITY Simple    '<ulink url="../libraries/Cabal/Distribution-Simple.html">Distribution.Simple</ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Make      '<ulink url="../libraries/Cabal/Distribution-Make.html">Distribution.Make</ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY License   '<ulink url="../libraries/Cabal/Distribution-License.html#t:License"><literal>License</literal></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Extension '<ulink url="../libraries/Cabal/Language-Haskell-Extension.html#t:Extension"><literal>Extension</literal></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY BuildType '<ulink url="../libraries/Cabal/Distribution-PackageDescription.html#t:BuildType"><literal>BuildType</literal></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Alex '<ulink url="http://www.haskell.org/alex/"><command>alex</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Autoconf '<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/autoconf/"><command>autoconf</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY C2hs '<ulink url="http://www.cse.unsw.edu.au/~chak/haskell/c2hs/"><command>c2hs</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Cpphs '<ulink url="http://www.haskell.org/cpphs/"><command>cpphs</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Greencard '<ulink url="http://www.haskell.org/greencard/"><command>greencard</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Haddock '<ulink url="http://www.haskell.org/haddock/"><command>haddock</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY HsColour '<ulink url="http://www.cs.york.ac.uk/fp/darcs/hscolour/"><command>HsColour</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY Happy '<ulink url="http://www.haskell.org/happy/"><command>happy</command></ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY HackageDB '<ulink url="http://hackage.haskell.org/">HackageDB</ulink>'>
    <!ENTITY PkgConfig '<ulink url="http://pkg-config.freedesktop.org/">pkg-config</ulink>'>
  ]>

<article>
  <title>Common Architecture for Building Applications and Libraries</title>
  <subtitle>User's Guide</subtitle>

  <abstract>
    <para><firstterm>Cabal</firstterm> aims to simplify the
      distribution of <ulink url="http://www.haskell.org/">Haskell</ulink>
      software.  It does this by specifying a number of interfaces between
      package authors, builders and users, as well as providing a library
      implementing these interfaces.</para>
  </abstract>

  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Developers write Cabal packages. These can be for libraries or
      executables. This involves writing the code obviously and also creating a
      <literal>.cabal</literal> file. The .cabal file contains some information
      about the package. Some of this information is needed to actually build
      the package and some is just useful for identifying the package when it
      comes to distribution.
    </para>
    <programlisting>
name:     Foo
version:  1.0

library
  build-depends:   base
  exposed-modules: Foo
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      Users install Cabal packages so they can use them. It is not expected
      that users will have to modify any of the information in the
      <literal>.cabal</literal> file. Cabal does provide a number of ways for
      a user to customise how and where a package is installed. They can decide
      where a package will be installed, which Haskell implementation to use
      and whether to build optimised code or build with the ability to profile
      code.
    </para>
    <programlisting>
tar -xzf Foo-1.0.tar.gz
cd Foo-1.0
runhaskell Setup configure --with-compiler=ghc-6.4.2 --user
runhaskell Setup build
runhaskell Setup install
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      One of the purposes of Cabal is to make it easier to build a package with
      different Haskell implementations. So it provides abstractions of
      features present in different Haskell implementations and wherever
      possible it is best to take advantage of these to increase portability.
      Where necessary however it is possible to use specific features of
      specific implementations. For example one of the pieces of information a
      package author can put in the package's <literal>.cabal</literal> file is
      what language extensions the code uses. This is far preferable to
      specifying flags for a specific compiler as it allows Cabal to pick the
      right flags for the Haskell implementation that the user picks. It also
      allows Cabal to figure out if the language extension is even supported by
      the Haskell implementation that the user picks. Where compiler-specific
      options are needed however, there is an "escape hatch" available. The
      developer can specify implementation-specific options and more generally
      there is a configuration mechanism to customise many aspects of how a
      package is built depending on the Haskell implementation, the Operating
      system, computer architecture and user-specified configuration flags.
    </para>
    <programlisting>
name:     Foo
version:  1.0

library
  build-depends:   base
  exposed-modules: Foo
  extensions:	   ForeignFunctionInterface
  ghc-options:     -Wall
  nhc98-options:   -K4m
  if os(windows)
    build-depends: Win32
    </programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="packages">
    <title>Packages</title>

    <para>A <firstterm>package</firstterm> is the unit of distribution
      for the Cabal.  Its purpose, when installed, is to make available
      either or both of:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A library, exposing a number of Haskell modules.  A library
          may also contain <firstterm>hidden</firstterm> modules, which
          are used internally but not available to clients.<footnote>
            <para>Hugs doesn't support module hiding.</para>
          </footnote>
          </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>One or more Haskell programs.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>However having both a library and executables in a package
      does not work very well; if the executables depend on the library,
      they must explicitly list all the modules they directly or
      indirectly import from that library.</para>

    <para>Internally, the package may consist of much more than a
    bunch of Haskell modules: it may also have C source code and
    header files, source code meant for preprocessing, documentation,
    test cases, auxiliary tools etc.</para>

    <para>A package is identified by a globally-unique
      <firstterm>package name</firstterm>, which consists of one or
      more alphanumeric words separated by hyphens.  To avoid ambiguity,
      each of these words should contain at least one letter.
      Chaos will result if two distinct packages with the
      same name are installed on the same system, but there is not
      yet a mechanism for allocating these names.
      A particular version of the package is distinguished by a
      <firstterm>version number</firstterm>, consisting of a sequence
      of one or more integers separated by dots.  These can be combined
      to form a single text string called the <firstterm>package
      ID</firstterm>, using a hyphen to separate the name from the
      version, e.g. <quote><literal>HUnit-1.1</literal></quote>.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Packages are not part of the Haskell language;
        they simply populate the hierarchical space of module names.
        In GHC 6.6 and later a program may contain multiple modules
        with the same name if they come from separate packages; in all
        other current Haskell systems packages may not overlap in the
        modules they provide, including hidden modules.</para>
    </note>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="authors">
    <title>Creating a package</title>

    <para>Suppose you have a directory hierarchy containing the source
      files that make up your package.  You will need to add two more
      files to the root directory of the package:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename><replaceable>package</replaceable>.cabal</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>a Unicode UTF-8 text file containing a package description
            (for details of the syntax of this file, see
            <xref linkend="pkg-descr"/>)</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>Setup.hs</filename> or
          <filename>Setup.lhs</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>a single-module Haskell program to perform various
            setup tasks (with the interface described in
            <xref linkend="builders"/>).  This module should import only
            modules that will be present in all Haskell implementations,
            including modules of the Cabal library.  In most cases it
            will be trivial, calling on the Cabal library to do most of
            the work.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>Once you have these, you can create a source bundle of this
      directory for distribution.  Building of the package is discussed in
      <xref linkend="builders"/>.</para>

    <example id="simple-library-example">
      <title>A package containing a simple library</title>
      <para>The HUnit package contains a file <filename>HUnit.cabal</filename>
        containing:</para>
      <programlisting>
Name:		HUnit
Version:	1.1.1
Cabal-Version:  >= 1.2
License:	BSD3
License-File:	LICENSE
Author:		Dean Herington
Homepage:	http://hunit.sourceforge.net/
Category:	Testing
Synopsis:	A unit testing framework for Haskell

Library
  Build-Depends:	base
  Exposed-modules:
    Test.HUnit.Base, Test.HUnit.Lang, Test.HUnit.Terminal,
    Test.HUnit.Text, Test.HUnit
  Extensions:	CPP
</programlisting>
      <para>and the following <filename>Setup.hs</filename>:</para>
      <programlisting>
import Distribution.Simple
main = defaultMain</programlisting>
    </example>

    <example id="simple-executable-example">
      <title>A package containing executable programs</title>
      <programlisting>
Name:           TestPackage
Version:        0.0
Cabal-Version:  >= 1.2
License:        BSD3
Author:         Angela Author
Synopsis:       Small package with two programs
Build-Type:     Simple

Executable program1
  Build-Depends:  HUnit
  Main-Is:        Main.hs
  Hs-Source-Dirs: prog1

Executable program2
  Main-Is:        Main.hs
  Build-Depends:  HUnit
  Hs-Source-Dirs: prog2
  Other-Modules:  Utils
</programlisting>
      <para>with <filename>Setup.hs</filename> the same as above.</para>
    </example>

    <example id="simple-library-executable-example">
      <title>A package containing a library and executable programs</title>
      <programlisting>
Name:            TestPackage
Version:         0.0
Cabal-Version:   >= 1.2
License:         BSD3
Author:          Angela Author
Synopsis:        Package with library and two programs
Build-Type:      Simple

Library
  Build-Depends:   HUnit
  Exposed-Modules: A, B, C

Executable program1
  Main-Is:         Main.hs
  Hs-Source-Dirs:  prog1
  Other-Modules:   A, B

Executable program2
  Main-Is:         Main.hs
  Hs-Source-Dirs:  prog2
  Other-Modules:   A, C, Utils
</programlisting>
      <para>with <filename>Setup.hs</filename> the same as above.
      Note that any library modules required (directly or indirectly)
      by an executable must be listed again.</para>
    </example>

    <para>The trivial setup script used in these examples uses
      the <firstterm>simple build infrastructure</firstterm>
      provided by the Cabal library (see &Simple;).
      The simplicity lies in its interface rather that its implementation.
      It automatically handles preprocessing with standard preprocessors,
      and builds packages for all the Haskell implementations (except
      nhc98, for now).</para>

    <para>The simple build infrastructure can also handle packages
      where building is governed by system-dependent parameters,
      if you specify a little more (see <xref linkend="system-dependent"/>).
      A few packages require more elaborate solutions
      (see <xref linkend="complex-packages"/>).</para>

    <sect2 id="pkg-descr">
      <title>Package descriptions</title>

      <para>The package description file must have a name ending in
        <quote><literal>.cabal</literal></quote>.  It must be a Unicode text
	file encoded using valid UTF-8. There must be exactly
        one such file in the directory.  The first part of the name is
        usually the package name, and some of the tools that operate
        on Cabal packages require this.</para>

      <para>In the package description file, lines whose first
      non-whitespace characters
      are <quote><literal>--</literal></quote> are treated as comments
      and ignored.</para>

      <para>This file should contain of a number global property
      descriptions and several sections.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The global properties describe the package as a whole,
	  such as name, license, author, etc.  (see <xref
	  linkend="general-fields"/>).</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Optionally, a number of <firstterm>configuration
	  flags</firstterm> can be declared.  These can be used to
	  enable or disable certain features of a package. (see <xref
	  linkend="configurations"/>).</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The (optional) library section specifies the library
	  properties (see <xref linkend="library"/>) and relevant build
	  information (see <xref linkend="buildinfo"/>).</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Following is an arbitrary number of executable sections
	  which describe an executable program and (see <xref
	  linkend="executable"/>) relevant build information (see <xref
	  linkend="buildinfo"/>).</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Each section consists of a number of property descriptions
      in the form of field/value pairs, with a syntax roughly like mail
      message headers.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
          <para>Case is not significant in field names,
            but is significant in field values.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
          <para>To continue a field value, indent the next line
          relative to the field name.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
          <para>Field names may be indented, but all field values in
          the same section must use the same indentation.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
          <para>Tabs are <emphasis>not</emphasis> allowed as
          indentation characters due to a missing standard
          interpretation of tab width.</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
          <para>To get a blank line in a field value, use an indented
            <quote><literal>.</literal></quote></para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The syntax of the value depends on the field.  Field types
        include:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <replaceable>token</replaceable>
          </term>
          <term>
            <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
          </term>
          <term>
            <replaceable>directory</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Either a sequence of one or more non-space non-comma
              characters, or a quoted string in Haskell 98 lexical syntax.
              Unless otherwise stated, relative filenames and directories
              are interpreted from the package root directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
          </term>
          <term>
            <replaceable>URL</replaceable>
          </term>
          <term>
            <replaceable>address</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>An arbitrary, uninterpreted string.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <replaceable>identifier</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A letter followed by zero or more alphanumerics
              or underscores.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <replaceable>compiler</replaceable>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>A compiler flavor (one
              of: <literal>GHC</literal>, <literal>NHC</literal>,
	          <literal>YHC</literal>, <literal>Hugs</literal>,
	          <literal>HBC</literal>, <literal>Helium</literal>,
                  <literal>JHC</literal>, or <literal>LHC</literal>)
              followed by a version range.  For example,
              <literal>GHC ==6.10.3</literal>,
	      or <literal>LHC &gt;=0.6 &amp;&amp; &lt;0.8</literal>.
            </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <note>
        <title>Modules and preprocessors</title>
        <para>Haskell module names listed in the
          <literal>exposed-modules</literal> and
          <literal>other-modules</literal> fields may
          correspond to Haskell source files, i.e. with names
          ending in <quote><literal>.hs</literal></quote> or
          <quote><literal>.lhs</literal></quote>, or to inputs for
          various Haskell preprocessors.
          The simple build infrastructure understands the extensions
          <quote><literal>.gc</literal></quote> (&Greencard;),
          <quote><literal>.chs</literal></quote> (&C2hs;),
          <quote><literal>.hsc</literal></quote> (<command>hsc2hs</command>),
          <quote><literal>.y</literal></quote> and
          <quote><literal>.ly</literal></quote> (&Happy;),
          <quote><literal>.x</literal></quote> (&Alex;)
          and
          <quote><literal>.cpphs</literal></quote> (&Cpphs;).
          When building, Cabal will automatically run the appropriate
          preprocessor and compile the Haskell module it produces.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Some fields take lists of values, which
        are optionally separated by commas, except for the
        <literal>build-depends</literal> field, where the commas are
        mandatory.</para>

      <para>Some fields are marked as required.  All others are optional,
        and unless otherwise specified have empty default values.</para>

      <sect3 id="general-fields">
        <title>Package properties</title>

        <para>These fields may occur in the first top-level properties
        section and describe the package as a whole:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>name:</literal> <replaceable>package-name</replaceable>
              (required)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The unique name of the package
                (see <xref linkend="packages"/>), without the version
                number.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>version:</literal> <replaceable>numbers</replaceable>
              (required)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The package version number, usually consisting of a
                sequence of natural numbers separated by dots.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>cabal-version:</literal> <replaceable>&gt;, &lt;=, etc. &amp; numbers</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The version of Cabal required for this package.
              Since, with Cabal version 1.2 the syntax of package
              descriptions has changed, this is now a required field.
              List the field early in your <literal>.cabal</literal>
              file so that it will appear as a syntax error before any
              others, since old versions of Cabal unfortunately do not
              recognize this field.</para>
	      <para>For compatibility, files written in the old syntax
	      are still recognized.  Thus if you don't require
	      features introduced with or after Cabal version 1.2, you
	      may write your package description file using the old
	      syntax.  Please consult the user's guide of that Cabal
	      version for a description of that syntax.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>build-type:</literal> <replaceable>identifier</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The type of build used by this package.
                Build types are the constructors of the &BuildType; type,
                defaulting to <literal>Custom</literal>.
                If this field is given a value other than
                <literal>Custom</literal>, some tools such as
                <literal>cabal-install</literal> will be able to
                build the package without using the setup script. So if you are
                just using the default <literal>Setup.hs</literal> then set
                the build type as <literal>Simple</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

           <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>license:</literal> <replaceable>identifier</replaceable>
              (default: <literal>AllRightsReserved</literal>)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The type of license under which this package is
                distributed.  License names are the constants of the
                &License; type.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>license-file:</literal>
              <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The name of a file containing the precise license
                for this package. It will be installed with the package.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>copyright:</literal>
              <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The content of a copyright notice, typically the
                name of the holder of the copyright on the package and
                the year(s) from which copyright is claimed.</para>
              <para>For example:
              <literal>Copyright: (c) 2006-2007 Joe Bloggs</literal>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>author:</literal>
              <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The original author of the package.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>maintainer:</literal>
              <replaceable>address</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The current maintainer or maintainers of the package.
                This is an e-mail address to which users should send bug
                reports, feature requests and patches.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>stability:</literal>
              <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The stability level of the package, e.g.
                <literal>alpha</literal>, <literal>experimental</literal>,
                <literal>provisional</literal>,
                <literal>stable</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>homepage:</literal> <replaceable>URL</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The package homepage.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>bug-reports:</literal> <replaceable>URL</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The URL where users should direct bug reports. This would
                normally be either:
                <itemizedlist>
	              <listitem>
                        <para>
                          A <literal>mailto:</literal> URL, eg for a person or a
                          mailing list.
                        </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>
                          An <literal>http:</literal> (or <literal>https:</literal>)
                          URL for an online bug tracking system.
                        </para>
	              </listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
              For example Cabal itself uses a web-based bug tracking system
              <programlisting>bug-reports: http://hackage.haskell.org/trac/hackage/</programlisting>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>package-url:</literal> <replaceable>URL</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The location of a source bundle for the package.
                The distribution should be a Cabal package.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>synopsis:</literal>
              <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A very short description of the package, for use in
                a table of packages.  This is your headline, so keep
                it short (one line) but as informative as possible.
                Save space by not including the package name or saying
                it's written in Haskell.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>description:</literal>
              <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Description of the package.  This may be several
                paragraphs, and should be aimed at a Haskell programmer
                who has never heard of your package before.</para>

              <para>For library packages, this field is used as
                prologue text by <command>setup haddock</command>
                (see <xref linkend="setup-haddock"/>), and thus may
                contain the same markup as &Haddock; documentation
                comments.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>category:</literal>
              <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A classification category for future use by the
                package catalogue <firstterm>Hackage</firstterm>.  These
                categories have not yet been specified, but the upper
                levels of the module hierarchy make a good start.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>tested-with:</literal>
              <replaceable>compiler list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of compilers and versions against which the
                package has been tested (or at least built).</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>data-files:</literal>
              <replaceable>filename list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of files to be installed for run-time use by
                the package.  This is useful for packages that use a
                large amount of static data, such as tables of values
                or code templates.  For details on how to find these
                files at run-time, see
                <xref linkend="paths-module"/>.</para>
              <para>
		A limited form of <literal>*</literal> wildcards in file names,
		for example <literal>data-files: images/*.png</literal> matches
		all the <literal>.png</literal> files in the
		<literal>images</literal> directory.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		The limitation is that <literal>*</literal> wildcards are only
		allowed in place of the file name, not in the directory name or
		file extension.  In particular, wildcards do not include
		directories contents recursively. Furthermore, if a wildcard is
		used it must be used with an extension, so <literal>data-files:
		data/*</literal> is not allowed. When matching a wildcard plus
		extension, a file's full extension must match exactly, so
		<literal>*.gz</literal> matches <literal>foo.gz</literal> but
		not <literal>foo.tar.gz</literal>. A wildcard that does not
		match any files is an error.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		The reason for providing only a very limited form of wildcard
		is to concisely express the common case of a large number of
		related files of the same file type without making it too easy
		to accidentally include unwanted files.
	      </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>data-dir:</literal>
              <replaceable>directory</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The directory where Cabal looks for data files to install,
                relative to the source directory. By default, Cabal will look
                in the source directory itself.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>extra-source-files:</literal>
              <replaceable>filename list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of additional files to be included in source
                distributions built with <command>setup sdist</command>
                (see <xref linkend="setup-sdist"/>).</para>
              <para>As with <literal>data-files</literal> it can use a limited
		form of <literal>*</literal> wildcards in file names.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>extra-tmp-files:</literal>
              <replaceable>filename list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of additional files or directories to be
                removed by <command>setup clean</command>
                (see <xref linkend="setup-clean"/>).
                These would typically be additional files created by
                additional hooks, such as the scheme described in
                <xref linkend="system-dependent"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="library">
        <title>Library</title>

        <para>The library section should contain the following
        fields:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>exposed-modules:</literal>
              <replaceable>identifier list</replaceable>
              (required if this package contains a library)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of modules added by this package.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>exposed:</literal> <replaceable>boolean</replaceable>
              (default: <literal>True</literal>)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
		Some Haskell compilers (notably GHC) support the notion of
		packages being <quote>exposed</quote> or <quote>hidden</quote>
		which means the modules they provide can be easily imported
		without always having to specify which package they come from.
		However this only works effectively if the modules provided by
		all exposed packages do not overlap (otherwise a module import
		would be ambiguous).
	      </para>
	      <para>
		Almost all new libraries use hierarchical module names that do
		not clash, so it is very uncommon to have to use this field.
		However it may be necessary to set <literal>exposed:
		False</literal> for some old libraries that use a flat module
		namespace or where it is known that the exposed modules would
		clash with other common modules.
	      </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <para>The library section may also contain build information fields
          (see <xref linkend="buildinfo"/>).</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="executable">
        <title>Executables</title>

        <para>Executable sections (if present) describe executable
        programs contained in the package and must have an argument
        after the section label, which defines the name of the
        executable.  This is a freeform argument but may not contain
        spaces.</para>

        <para>The executable may be described using the following
        fields, as well as build information fields (see <xref
        linkend="buildinfo"/>).</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>main-is:</literal> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
              (required)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The name of the <filename>.hs</filename> or
                <filename>.lhs</filename> file containing the
                <literal>Main</literal> module. Note that it is the
                <filename>.hs</filename> filename that must be listed, even if
                that file is generated using a preprocessor. The source
                file must be relative to one of the directories listed in
                <literal>hs-source-dirs</literal>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="buildinfo">
        <title>Build information</title>

        <para>The following fields may be optionally present in a
        library or executable section, and give information for the
        building of the corresponding library or executable.  See also
        <xref linkend="system-dependent"/> and <xref linkend="configurations"/>
        for a way to supply system-dependent values for these
        fields.</para>

        <variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>build-depends:</literal>
              <replaceable>package list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of packages needed to build this one. Each package
	      can be annotated with a version constraint.
	      </para>
	      <para>
                Version constraints use the operators <literal>==, >=, >,
		&lt;, &lt;=</literal> and a version number. Multiple
		constraints can be combined using <literal>&amp;&amp;</literal>
		or <literal>||</literal>. If no version constraint is
		specified, any version is assumed to be	acceptable.
		For example:
	      </para>
              <programlisting>
library
  build-depends:
    base >= 2,
    foo >= 1.2 &amp;&amp; &lt; 1.3,
    bar
</programlisting>
	      <para>
	        Dependencies like <literal>foo >= 1.2 &amp;&amp; &lt; 1.3</literal> turn
		out to be very common because it is recommended	practise for
		package versions to correspond to API versions. There is a
		special syntax to support this use:
	      </para>
              <programlisting>build-depends: foo ==1.2.*</programlisting>
	      <para>
	        It is only syntactic sugar. It is exactly equivalent to
		<literal>foo >= 1.2 &amp;&amp; &lt; 1.3</literal>.
	      </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>other-modules:</literal>
              <replaceable>identifier list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of modules used by the component
                but not exposed to users.  For a library component, these
                would be hidden modules of the library.  For an executable,
                these would be auxiliary modules to be linked with the
                file named in the <literal>main-is</literal> field.</para>
	      <note>
                <para>Every module in the package <emphasis>must</emphasis> be
		listed in one of <literal>other-modules</literal>,
		<literal>exposed-modules</literal> or
		<literal>main-is</literal> fields.
		</para>
	      </note>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>hs-source-dirs:</literal>
              <replaceable>directory list</replaceable>
              (default: <quote><literal>.</literal></quote>)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Root directories for the module hierarchy.</para>

              <para>For backwards compatibility, the old variant
                <literal>hs-source-dir</literal> is also recognized.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>extensions:</literal>
              <replaceable>identifier list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of Haskell extensions used by every module.
                Extension names are the constructors of the &Extension; type.
                These determine corresponding compiler options.
                In particular, <literal>CPP</literal> specifies that
                Haskell source files are to be preprocessed with a
                C preprocessor.</para>

              <para>Extensions used only by one module may be specified
                by placing a <literal>LANGUAGE</literal> pragma in the
                source file affected, e.g.:</para>
              <programlisting>{-# LANGUAGE CPP, MultiParamTypeClasses #-}</programlisting>
	      <note>
                <para>GHC versions prior to 6.6 do not support the
                  <literal>LANGUAGE</literal> pragma.</para>
	      </note>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>build-tools:</literal>
              <replaceable>program list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of programs, possibly annotated with versions,
                needed to build this package,
                e.g. <literal>c2hs > 0.15, cpphs</literal>.
                If no version constraint is specified, any version is
                assumed to be acceptable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>buildable:</literal> <replaceable>boolean</replaceable>
              (default: <literal>True</literal>)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Is the component buildable?
                Like some of the other fields below, this field is
                more useful with the slightly more elaborate form of
                the simple build infrastructure described in
                <xref linkend="system-dependent"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>ghc-options:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Additional options for GHC.  You can often achieve
                the same effect using the <literal>extensions</literal>
                field, which is preferred.</para>

              <para>Options required only by one module may be specified
                by placing an <literal>OPTIONS_GHC</literal> pragma in the
                source file affected.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>ghc-prof-options:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Additional options for GHC when the package is built
                with profiling enabled.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>ghc-shared-options:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Additional options for GHC when the package is
              built as shared library.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>hugs-options:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Additional options for Hugs.  You can often achieve
                the same effect using the <literal>extensions</literal>
                field, which is preferred.</para>

              <para>Options required only by one module may be specified
                by placing an <literal>OPTIONS_HUGS</literal> pragma in the
                source file affected.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>nhc98-options:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Additional options for nhc98.  You can often achieve
                the same effect using the <literal>extensions</literal>
                field, which is preferred.</para>

              <para>Options required only by one module may be specified
                by placing an <literal>OPTIONS_NHC98</literal> pragma in the
                source file affected.</para>

              <para>Warning: Cabal does not currently support building
                libraries or executables with nhc98 anyway.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>includes:</literal>
              <replaceable>filename list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of header files to be included in any
              compilations via C.  This field applies to both header
              files that are already installed on the system and to
              those coming with the package to be installed.  These files
              typically contain function prototypes for foreign imports
              used by the package.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>install-includes:</literal>
              <replaceable>filename list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of header files from this package to be
              installed into
              <literal>$libdir/includes</literal> when the package
              is installed.  Files listed in
              <literal>install-includes:</literal> should be found in
              relative to the top of the source tree or relative to one of the
              directories listed in <literal>include-dirs</literal>.</para>

	      <para><literal>install-includes</literal> is typically
	      used to name header files that contain prototypes for
	      foreign imports used in Haskell code in this package,
	      for which the C implementations are also provided with
	      the package.  Note that to include them when compiling
	      the package itself, they need to be listed in the
	      <literal>includes:</literal> field as well.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>include-dirs:</literal>
              <replaceable>directory list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of directories to search for header files,
                when preprocessing with <command>c2hs</command>,
                <command>hsc2hs</command>, <command>ffihugs</command>,
                <command>cpphs</command> or the C preprocessor,
		and also when compiling via C.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>c-sources:</literal>
              <replaceable>filename list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of C source files to be compiled
                and linked with the Haskell files.</para>

              <para>If you use this field, you should also name the
                C files in <literal>CFILES</literal> pragmas in the
                Haskell source files that use them, e.g.:
                <screen>{-# CFILES dir/file1.c dir/file2.c #-}</screen>
                These are ignored by the compilers, but needed by Hugs.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>extra-libraries:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of extra libraries to link with.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>extra-lib-dirs:</literal>
              <replaceable>directory list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of directories to search for libraries.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>cc-options:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Command-line arguments to be passed to the C compiler.
                Since the arguments are compiler-dependent, this field
                is more useful with the setup described in
                <xref linkend="system-dependent"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>ld-options:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Command-line arguments to be passed to the linker.
                Since the arguments are compiler-dependent, this field
                is more useful with the setup described in
                <xref linkend="system-dependent"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>pkgconfig-depends:</literal>
              <replaceable>package list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>A list of &PkgConfig; packages, needed to build this
                package. They can be annotated with versions,
                e.g. <literal>gtk+-2.0 >= 2.10, cairo >= 1.0</literal>.
                If no version constraint is specified, any version is
                assumed to be acceptable. Cabal uses
                <literal>pkg-config</literal> to find if the packages are
                available on the system and to find the extra compilation and
                linker options needed to use the packages.
              </para>
              <para> If you need to bind to a C library that supports
                <literal>pkg-config</literal> (use
                <literal>pkg-config --list-all</literal> to find out if it is
                supported) then it is much preferable to use this field rather
                than hard code options into the other fields.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>frameworks:</literal>
              <replaceable>token list</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>On Darwin/MacOS X, a list of frameworks to link to.
                See Apple's developer documentation for more details
                on frameworks.  This entry is ignored on all other
                platforms.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="configurations">
	<title>Configurations</title>
	<para>Library and executable sections may include conditional
	blocks, which test for various system parameters and
	configuration flags.  The flags mechanism is rather generic,
	but most of the time a flag represents certain feature, that
	can be switched on or off by the package user.</para>
	<para>Here is an example package description file using
	configurations:</para>
	<example id="package-with-configurations-example">
	  <title>A package containing a library and executable programs</title>

	<programlisting>Name: Test1
Version: 0.0.1
Cabal-Version: >= 1.2
License: BSD3
Author:  Jane Doe
Synopsis: Test package to test configurations
Category: Example

Flag Debug
  Description: Enable debug support
  Default:     False

Flag WebFrontend
  Description: Include API for web frontend.
  -- Cabal checks if the configuration is possible, first
  -- with this flag set to True and if not it tries with False

Library
  Build-Depends:   base
  Exposed-Modules: Testing.Test1
  Extensions:      CPP

  if flag(debug)
    GHC-Options: -DDEBUG
    if !os(windows)
      CC-Options: "-DDEBUG"
    else
      CC-Options: "-DNDEBUG"

  if flag(webfrontend)
    Build-Depends: cgi > 0.42
    Other-Modules: Testing.WebStuff

Executable test1
  Main-is: T1.hs
  Other-Modules: Testing.Test1
  Build-Depends: base

  if flag(debug)
    CC-Options: "-DDEBUG"
    GHC-Options: -DDEBUG
</programlisting>
	</example>
	<sect4>
	 <title>Layout</title>
	 <para>Flags, conditionals, library and executable sections use layout to
     indicate structure. This is very similar to the Haskell layout rule.
     Entries in a section have to all be indented to the same level which must
     be more than the section header. Tabs are not allowed to be used for
     indentation.</para>

	 <para>As an alternative to using layout you can also use explicit braces
     <literal>{}</literal>. In this case the indentation of entries in a
     section does not matter, though different fields within a block must be
     on different lines. Here is a bit of the above example again, using
     braces:</para>
   <example id="configurations-with-braces-example">
	  <title>Using explicit braces rather than indentation for layout</title>

	  <programlisting>Name: Test1
Version: 0.0.1
Cabal-Version: >= 1.2
License: BSD3
Author:  Jane Doe
Synopsis: Test package to test configurations
Category: Example

Flag Debug {
  Description: Enable debug support
  Default:     False
}

Library {
  Build-Depends:   base
  Exposed-Modules: Testing.Test1
  Extensions:      CPP
  if flag(debug) {
    GHC-Options: -DDEBUG
    if !os(windows) {
      CC-Options: "-DDEBUG"
    } else {
      CC-Options: "-DNDEBUG"
    }
  }
}
</programlisting>
	  </example>
	</sect4>
	<sect4>
	 <title>Configuration Flags</title>
	 <para>A flag section takes the flag name as an argument and
	 may contain the following fields.</para>
	 <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>description:</literal>
              <replaceable>freeform</replaceable>
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The description of this flag.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>default:</literal>
              <replaceable>boolean</replaceable>
	      (default: <literal>True</literal>)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The default value of this flag.</para>
	      <para>Note that this value may be overridden in several
	      ways (see <xref linkend="flag-control"/>).  The
	      rationale for having flags default to True is that users
	      usually want new features as soon as they are available.
	      Flags representing features that are not (yet)
	      recommended for most users (such as experimental
	      features or debugging support) should therefore
	      explicitly override the default to False.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <literal>manual:</literal>
              <replaceable>boolean</replaceable>
              (default: <literal>False</literal>)
            </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>By default, Cabal will first try to satisfy
              dependencies with the default flag value and then,
              if that is not possible, with the negated value.
              However, if the flag is manual, then the default
              value (which can be overridden by commandline flags)
              will be used.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
	</sect4>
	<sect4 id="conditionals">
	  <title>Conditional Blocks</title>
	  <para>Conditional blocks may appear anywhere inside a
	  library or executable section.  They have to follow rather
	  strict formatting rules.</para>
	  <para>Conditional blocks must always be of the shape
	  <literallayout>
	    <literal>if </literal><replaceable>condition</replaceable>
	         <replaceable>property-descriptions-or-conditionals*</replaceable>
    </literallayout>or
	  <literallayout>
	    <literal>if </literal><replaceable>condition</replaceable>
	         <replaceable>property-descriptions-or-conditionals*</replaceable>
	    <literal>else</literal>
	         <replaceable>property-descriptions-or-conditionals*</replaceable>
	  </literallayout></para>

	  <para>Note that the <literal>if</literal> and the condition have to
	  be all on the same line.</para>

	</sect4>
	<sect4 id="conditions">
	  <title>Conditions</title>
	  <para>Conditions can be formed using boolean tests and the
	  boolean operators <literal>||</literal> (disjunction /
	  logical "or"), <literal>&amp;&amp;</literal> (conjunction /
	  logical "and"), or <literal>!</literal> (negation / logical
	  "not").  The unary <literal>!</literal> takes highest
	  precedence, <literal>||</literal> takes lowest.  Precedence
	  levels may be overridden through the use of parentheses.
	  For example, <literal>os(darwin) &amp;&amp; !arch(i386) || os(freebsd)</literal>
          is equivalent to <literal>(os(darwin) &amp;&amp; !(arch(i386))) || os(freebsd)</literal>.
	  </para>
	  <para>The following tests are currently supported.</para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		<literal>os(</literal>
		<replaceable>name</replaceable>
		<literal>)</literal>
	      </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Tests if the current operating system is
              <replaceable>name</replaceable>.  The argument is tested
              against <literal>System.Info.os</literal> on 
              the target system. There is unfortunately some disagreement
              between Haskell implementations about the standard values of
              <literal>System.Info.os</literal>. Cabal canonicalises it so
              that in particular <literal>os(windows)</literal> works on all
              implementations. If the canonicalised os names match, this test
              evaluates to true, otherwise false. The match is
              case-insensitive. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		<literal>arch(</literal>
		<replaceable>name</replaceable>
		<literal>)</literal>
	      </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Tests if the current architecture is
              <replaceable>name</replaceable>.  The argument is matched
              against <literal>System.Info.arch</literal> on the target system.
              If the arch names match, this test evaluates to true,
              otherwise false. The match is case-insensitive. </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		<literal>impl(</literal>
		<replaceable>compiler</replaceable>
		<literal>)</literal>
	      </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Tests for the configured Haskell implementation. An optional
              version constraint may be specified (for example
              <literal>impl(ghc >= 6.6.1)</literal>).  If the
              configured implementation is of the right type and matches the
              version constraint, then this evaluates to true,
              otherwise false. The match is case-insensitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>	      <term>
		<literal>flag(</literal>
		<replaceable>name</replaceable>
		<literal>)</literal>
	      </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Evaluates to the current assignment of the flag of
              the given name.  Flag names are case insensitive.
              Testing for flags that have not been introduced with a
              flag section is an error.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		<literal>true</literal>
	      </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Constant value true.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	      <term>
		<literal>false</literal>
	      </term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Constant value false.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

	</sect4>
	<sect4 id="conditional-resolution">
	  <title>Resolution of Conditions and Flags</title>
	  <para>If a package descriptions specifies configuration flags
	  the package user can control these in several ways (see
          <xref linkend="flag-control"/>). If the user does not fix the
          value of a flag, Cabal will try to find a flag assignment in the
	  following way.</para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>For each flag specified, it will assign its default
	      value, evaluate all conditions with this flag assignment,
	      and check if all dependencies can be satisfied.  If this
	      check succeeded, the package will be configured with those
	      flag assignments.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>If dependencies were missing, the last flag (as by
	      the order in which the flags were introduced in the
	      package description) is tried with its alternative value
	      and so on.  This continues until either an assignment is
	      found where all dependencies can be satisfied, or all
	      possible flag assignments have been tried.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

          <para>To put it another way, Cabal does a complete backtracking
          search to find a satisfiable package configuration. It is only the
          dependencies specified in the <literal>build-depends</literal> field
          in conditional blocks that determine if a particular flag assignment
          is satisfiable (<literal>build-tools</literal> are not considered).
          The order of the declaration and the default value of the flags
          determines the search order. Flags overridden on the command line fix
          the assignment of that flag, so no backtracking will be tried for
          that flag.</para>

	  <para>If no suitable flag assignment could be found, the
	  configuration phase will fail and a list of missing
	  dependencies will be printed.  Note that this resolution
	  process is exponential in the worst case (i.e., in the case
	  where dependencies cannot be satisfied).  There are some
	  optimizations applied internally, but the overall complexity
	  remains unchanged.</para>
	</sect4>
	<sect4 id="prop-combine">
          <title>Meaning of field values when using conditionals</title>
	  <para>During the configuration phase, a flag assignment is
	  chosen, all conditionals are evaluated, and the package description
          is combined into a flat package descriptions. If the same field
	  both inside a conditional and outside then they are combined using
          the following rules.</para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Boolean fields are combined using conjunction
	      (logical "and").</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>List fields are combined by appending the inner
	      items to the outer items, for example
	      <programlisting>Extensions: CPP
if impl(ghc) || impl(hugs)
  Extensions: MultiParamTypeClasses
</programlisting>
	    when compiled using Hugs or GHC will be combined to
	    <programlisting>Extensions: CPP, MultiParamTypeClasses</programlisting>
	    </para>
	    <para>Similarly, if two conditional sections appear at the
	    same nesting level, properties specified in the latter
	    will come after properties specified in the former.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>All other fields must not be specified in ambiguous ways.  For example
	      <programlisting>Main-is: Main.hs
if flag(useothermain)
  Main-is: OtherMain.hs
</programlisting>
	      will lead to an error.  Instead use
	      <programlisting>if flag(useothermain)
  Main-is: OtherMain.hs
else
  Main-is: Main.hs
</programlisting></para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="source-repos">
	      <title>Source Repositories</title>
	      <para>
	        It is often useful to be able to specify a source revision control
	        repository for a package. Cabal lets you specifying this information
	        in a relatively structured form which enables other tools to
	        interpret and make effective use of the information. For example the
	        information should be sufficient for an automatic tool to checkout
	        the sources.
	      </para>
	      <para>
	        Cabal supports specifying different information for various common
	        source control systems. Obviously not all automated tools will
	        support all source control systems.
	      </para>
	      <para>
	        Cabal supports specifying repositories for different use cases. By
	        declaring which case we mean automated tools can be more useful.
	        There are currently two kinds defined:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The <literal>head</literal> kind refers to the
            latest development branch of the package. This may be used for
            example to track activity of a project or as an indication to
            outside developers what sources to get for making new
            contributions.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
          <para>
            The <literal>this</literal> kind refers to the
            branch and tag of a repository that contains the sources for this
            version or release of a package. For most source control systems
            this involves specifying a tag, id or hash of some form and
            perhaps a branch. The purpose is to be able to reconstruct the
            sources corresponding to a particular package version. This might
            be used to indicate what sources to get if someone needs to fix a
            bug in an older branch that is no longer an active head branch.
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	      <para>
	        You can specify one kind or the other or both. As an example here are
	        the repositories for the Cabal library. Note that the
	        <literal>this</literal> kind of repo specifies a tag.
  	      <programlisting>
source-repository head
  type:     darcs
  location: http://darcs.haskell.org/cabal/

source-repository this
  type:     darcs
  location: http://darcs.haskell.org/cabal-branches/cabal-1.6/
  tag:      1.6.1
</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
          The exact fields are as follows:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>type:</literal>
            <replaceable>token</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The name of the source control system used for this repository.
              The currently recognised types are:
              <itemizedlist>
	              <listitem><para>darcs</para></listitem>
	              <listitem><para>git</para></listitem>
	              <listitem><para>svn</para></listitem>
	              <listitem><para>cvs</para></listitem>
	              <listitem><para>mercurial (or alias hg)</para></listitem>
	              <listitem><para>bazaar (or alias bzr)</para></listitem>
	              <listitem><para>arch</para></listitem>
	              <listitem><para>monotone</para></listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
              This field is required.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>location:</literal>
            <replaceable>URL</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The location of the repository. The exact form of this field
              depends on the repository type. For example:
              <itemizedlist>
	              <listitem>
	                <para>for darcs: <literal>http://code.haskell.org/foo/</literal></para>
	              </listitem>
	              <listitem>
	                <para>for git: <literal>git://github.com/foo/bar.git</literal></para>
	              </listitem>
	              <listitem>
	                <para>for CVS: <literal>anoncvs@cvs.foo.org:/cvs</literal></para>
	              </listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
              This field is required.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>module:</literal>
            <replaceable>token</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              CVS requires a named module, as each CVS server can host multiple
              named repositories.
            </para>
            <para>
              This field is required for the CVS repo type and should not be
              used otherwise.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>branch:</literal>
            <replaceable>token</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Many source control systems support the notion of a branch,
              as a distinct concept from having repositories in separate
              locations. For example CVS, SVN and git use branches while for
              darcs uses different locations for different branches. If you
              need to specify a branch to identify a your repository
              then specify it in this field.
            </para>
            <para>
              This field is optional.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>tag:</literal>
            <replaceable>token</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A tag identifies a particular state of a source repository. The
              tag can be used with a <literal>this</literal> repo kind to
              identify the state of a repo corresponding to a particular
              package version or release. The exact form of the tag depends on
              the repository type.
            </para>
            <para>
              This field is required for the <literal>this</literal> repo kind.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <literal>subdir:</literal>
            <replaceable>directory</replaceable>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Some projects put the sources for multiple packages under a
              single source repository. This field lets you specify the
              relative path from the root of the repository to the top
              directory for the package, ie the directory containing the
              package's <literal>.cabal</literal> file.
            </para>
            <para>
              This field is optional. It default to empty which corresponds to
              the root directory of the repository.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="paths-module">
      <title>Accessing data files from package code</title>
      <para>The placement on the target system of files listed in the
	<literal>data-files</literal> field varies between systems, and in
	some cases one can even move packages around after installation
	(see <xref linkend="prefix-independence"/>).  To enable packages
	to find these files in a portable way, Cabal generates a module
	called <literal>Paths_</literal><replaceable>pkgname</replaceable>
	(with any hyphens in <replaceable>pkgname</replaceable> replaced
	by underscores) during building, so that it may be imported by
	modules of the package.  This module defines a function
	<programlisting>getDataFileName :: FilePath -> IO FilePath</programlisting>
	If the argument is a filename listed in the
	<literal>data-files</literal> field, the result is the name
	of the corresponding file on the system on which the program
	is running.</para>
      <note>
        <para>If you decide to import the
	  <literal>Paths_</literal><replaceable>pkgname</replaceable> module then
	  it <emphasis>must</emphasis> be listed in the
	  <literal>other-modules</literal> field just like any other module in
	  your package.
	</para>
	<para>The <literal>Paths_</literal><replaceable>pkgname</replaceable>
	  module is not platform independent so it does not get included in the
	  source tarballs generated by <command>sdist</command>.
	</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="system-dependent">
      <title>System-dependent parameters</title>

      <para>For some packages, especially those interfacing with C
        libraries, implementation details and the build procedure depend
        on the build environment.  A variant of the simple build
        infrastructure (the <literal>build-type</literal>
        <literal>Configure</literal>) handles many such situations using
        a slightly longer <filename>Setup.hs</filename>:</para>
      <programlisting>
import Distribution.Simple
main = defaultMainWithHooks autoconfUserHooks</programlisting>

      <para>Most packages, however, would probably do better with
        configurations (see <xref linkend="configurations"/>).</para>

      <para>This program differs from <literal>defaultMain</literal>
        in two ways:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The package root directory must contain a shell script called
	    <filename>configure</filename>. The configure step will run the
	    script. This <filename>configure</filename> script may
            be produced by &Autoconf; or may be hand-written. The
	    <filename>configure</filename> script typically
            discovers information about the system and records it for
            later steps, e.g. by generating system-dependent header files
            for inclusion in C source files and preprocessed Haskell
            source files.  (Clearly this won't work for Windows without
            MSYS or Cygwin: other ideas are needed.)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the package root directory contains a file called
            <replaceable>package</replaceable><literal>.buildinfo</literal>
            after the configuration step, subsequent steps will read it
            to obtain additional settings for build information fields
            (see <xref linkend="buildinfo"/>), to be merged with the
            ones given in the <literal>.cabal</literal> file.
            In particular, this file may be generated by the
            <filename>configure</filename> script mentioned above,
            allowing these settings to vary depending on the build
            environment.</para>

          <para>The build information file should have the following
            structure:</para>
          <programlisting>
<replaceable>buildinfo</replaceable>

executable: <replaceable>name</replaceable>
<replaceable>buildinfo</replaceable>

executable: <replaceable>name</replaceable>
<replaceable>buildinfo</replaceable>

...</programlisting>
          <para>where each <replaceable>buildinfo</replaceable> consists
            of settings of fields listed in <xref linkend="buildinfo"/>.
            The first one (if present) relates to the library, while each
            of the others relate to the named executable.  (The names
            must match the package description, but you don't have to
            have entries for all of them.)</para>

        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>Neither of these files is required.  If they are absent, this
        setup script is equivalent to <literal>defaultMain</literal>.</para>

      <example id="autoconf-example">
        <title>Using autoconf</title>

        <para>(This example is for people familiar with the &Autoconf;
          tools.)</para>

        <para>In the X11 package, the file <filename>configure.ac</filename>
          contains:</para>
        <programlisting>
AC_INIT([Haskell X11 package], [1.1], [libraries@haskell.org], [X11])

# Safety check: Ensure that we are in the correct source directory.
AC_CONFIG_SRCDIR([X11.cabal])

# Header file to place defines in
AC_CONFIG_HEADERS([include/HsX11Config.h])

# Check for X11 include paths and libraries
AC_PATH_XTRA
AC_TRY_CPP([#include &lt;X11/Xlib.h&gt;],,[no_x=yes])

# Build the package if we found X11 stuff
if test "$no_x" = yes
then BUILD_PACKAGE_BOOL=False
else BUILD_PACKAGE_BOOL=True
fi
AC_SUBST([BUILD_PACKAGE_BOOL])

AC_CONFIG_FILES([X11.buildinfo])
AC_OUTPUT</programlisting>

        <para>Then the setup script will run the
          <literal>configure</literal> script, which checks for the
          presence of the X11 libraries and substitutes for variables
          in the file <filename>X11.buildinfo.in</filename>:</para>
        <programlisting>
buildable: @BUILD_PACKAGE_BOOL@
cc-options: @X_CFLAGS@
ld-options: @X_LIBS@</programlisting>

        <para>This generates a file <filename>X11.buildinfo</filename>
          supplying the parameters needed by later stages:</para>
        <programlisting>
buildable: True
cc-options:  -I/usr/X11R6/include
ld-options:  -L/usr/X11R6/lib</programlisting>

        <para>The <filename>configure</filename> script also generates
          a header file <filename>include/HsX11Config.h</filename>
          containing C preprocessor defines recording the results of
          various tests.  This file may be included by C source files
          and preprocessed Haskell source files in the package.</para>
      </example>

      <note>
        <para>Packages using these features will also need to list
          additional files such as <filename>configure</filename>,
          templates for <literal>.buildinfo</literal> files, files named
          only in <literal>.buildinfo</literal> files, header files and
          so on in the <literal>extra-source-files</literal> field,
          to ensure that they are included in source distributions.
          They should also list files and directories generated by
          <command>configure</command> in the
          <literal>extra-tmp-files</literal> field to ensure that they
          are removed by <command>setup clean</command>.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="cpp">
      <title>Conditional compilation</title>

      <para>Sometimes you want to write code that works with more than
      one version of a dependency.  You can specify a range of
        versions for the depenency in
      the <literal>build-depends</literal>, but how do you then write
        the code that can use different versions of the API?</para>
      
      <para>Haskell lets you preprocess your code using the C
        preprocessor (either the real C preprocessor, or
        <literal>cpphs</literal>).  To enable this,
        add <literal>extensions: CPP</literal> to your package
        description.  When using CPP, Cabal provides some pre-defined
        macros to let you test the version of dependent packages; for
        example, suppose your package works with either version 3 or
        version 4 of the <literal>base</literal> package, you could
        select the available version in your Haskell modules like
        this:</para> 
<programlisting>
#if MIN_VERSION_base(4,0,0)
... code that works with base-4 ...
#else
... code that works with base-3 ...
#endif
</programlisting>
<para>In general, Cabal supplies a
  macro <literal>MIN_VERSION_<replaceable>package</replaceable>(A,B,C)</literal>
  for each package depended on via <literal>build-depends</literal>.
  This macro is true if the actual version of the package in use is
  greater than or equal to <literal>A.B.C</literal> (using the
  conventional ordering on version numbers, which is lexicographic on
  the sequence, but numeric on each component, so for example 1.2.0 is
  greater than 1.0.3).</para>

      <para>Cabal places the definitions of these macros into an
        automatically-generated header file, which is included when
        preprocessing Haskell source code by passing options to the C
        preprocessor.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="complex-packages">
      <title>More complex packages</title>

      <para>For packages that don't fit the simple schemes described above,
        you have a few options:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can customize the simple build infrastructure
            using <firstterm>hooks</firstterm>.  These allow you to
            perform additional actions before and after each command is
            run, and also to specify additional preprocessors.  See
            <literal>UserHooks</literal> in &Simple; for the details,
            but note that this interface is experimental, and likely to
            change in future releases.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You could delegate all the work to <command>make</command>,
            though this is unlikely to be very portable.
            Cabal supports this with the <literal>build-type</literal>
            <literal>Make</literal> and a trivial setup library &Make;,
            which simply parses the command line arguments and invokes
            <command>make</command>.  Here <filename>Setup.hs</filename>
            looks like</para>
          <programlisting>
import Distribution.Make
main = defaultMain</programlisting>

          <para>The root directory of the package should contain
            a <filename>configure</filename> script, and, after
            that has run, a <filename>Makefile</filename> with a
            default target that builds the package, plus targets
            <literal>install</literal>, <literal>register</literal>,
            <literal>unregister</literal>, <literal>clean</literal>,
            <literal>dist</literal> and <literal>docs</literal>.
            Some options to commands are passed through as follows:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The <option>--with-hc-pkg</option>,
                <option>--prefix</option>, <option>--bindir</option>,
                <option>--libdir</option>, <option>--datadir</option>
                and <option>--libexecdir</option> options to the
                <literal>configure</literal> command are passed on to
                the <filename>configure</filename> script.
                In addition the value of the <option>--with-compiler</option>
                option is passed in a <option>--with-hc</option> option and
                all options specified with <option>--configure-option</option>=
                are passed on.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>the <literal>--destdir</literal> option to the
                <literal>copy</literal> command becomes a setting of a
                <literal>destdir</literal> variable on the invocation of
                <literal>make copy</literal>.  The supplied
                <literal>Makefile</literal> should provide a
                <literal>copy</literal> target, which will probably
                look like this:
<programlisting>
copy :
        $(MAKE) install prefix=$(destdir)/$(prefix) \
                        bindir=$(destdir)/$(bindir) \
                        libdir=$(destdir)/$(libdir) \
                        datadir=$(destdir)/$(datadir) \
                        libexecdir=$(destdir)/$(libexecdir)</programlisting>
</para>

            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can write your own setup script conforming to the
            interface of <xref linkend="builders"/>, possibly using
            the Cabal library for part of the work.  One option is to
            copy the source of <literal>Distribution.Simple</literal>,
            and alter it for your needs.  Good luck.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="builders">
    <title>Building and installing a package</title>
    <para>After you've unpacked a Cabal package, you can build it
      by moving into the root directory of the package and using the
      <filename>Setup.hs</filename> or <filename>Setup.lhs</filename>
      script there:</para>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>runhaskell Setup.hs</command>
      <arg><replaceable>command</replaceable></arg>
      <arg rep="repeat" choice="opt"><replaceable>option</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <para>where <replaceable>runhaskell</replaceable> might be
      <command>runhugs</command>, <command>runghc</command> or
      <command>runnhc</command>.  The <replaceable>command</replaceable>
      argument selects a particular step in the build/install process.
      You can also get a summary of the command syntax with</para>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>runhaskell Setup.hs <option>--help</option></command>
    </cmdsynopsis>

    <example id="system-install-example">
      <title>Building and installing a system package</title>
      <screen>
runhaskell Setup.hs configure --ghc
runhaskell Setup.hs build
runhaskell Setup.hs install</screen>
      <para>The first line readies the system to build the tool using GHC;
        for example, it checks that GHC exists on the system.  The second
        line performs the actual building, while the last both copies
        the build results to some permanent place and registers the
        package with GHC.</para>
    </example>

    <example id="user-install-example">
      <title>Building and installing a user package</title>
      <screen>
runhaskell Setup.hs configure --user
runhaskell Setup.hs build
runhaskell Setup.hs install</screen>
      <para>The package is installed under the user's home directory
        and is registered in the user's package database
        (<option>--user</option>).</para>
    </example>

    <example id="binary-package-example">
      <title>Creating a binary package</title>
      <para>When creating binary packages (e.g. for RedHat or
        Debian) one needs to create a tarball that can be sent to
        another system for unpacking in the root directory:</para>
      <screen>
runhaskell Setup.hs configure --prefix=/usr
runhaskell Setup.hs build
runhaskell Setup.hs copy --destdir=/tmp/mypkg
tar -czf mypkg.tar.gz /tmp/mypkg/</screen>

      <para>If the package contains a library, you need two additional
        steps:</para>
      <screen>
runhaskell Setup.hs register --gen-script
runhaskell Setup.hs unregister --gen-script</screen>
      <para>This creates shell scripts <filename>register.sh</filename>
        and <filename>unregister.sh</filename>, which must also be sent
        to the target system.  After unpacking there, the package must be
        registered by running the <filename>register.sh</filename> script.
        The <filename>unregister.sh</filename> script would be used
        in the uninstall procedure of the package.  Similar steps may
        be used for creating binary packages for Windows.</para>
    </example>

    <para>The following options are understood by all commands:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>--help</option>, <option>-h</option> or
          <option>-?</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>List the available options for the command.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>--verbose</option>=<replaceable>n</replaceable> or
          <option>-v</option><replaceable>n</replaceable>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Set the verbosity level (0-3).  The normal level is 1;
            a missing <replaceable>n</replaceable> defaults to 2.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The various commands and the additional options they support
      are described below.  In the simple build infrastructure, any
      other options will be reported as errors.</para>

    <sect2 id="setup-configure">
      <title>setup configure</title>
      <para>Prepare to build the package.  Typically, this step checks
	that the target platform is capable of building the package,
	and discovers platform-specific features that are needed during
	the build.</para>

      <para>The user may also adjust the behaviour of later stages using
	the options listed in the following subsections.  In the simple
	build infrastructure, the values supplied via these options are
	recorded in a private file read by later stages.</para>

      <para>If a user-supplied <filename>configure</filename>
	script is run (see <xref linkend="system-dependent"/>
	or <xref linkend="complex-packages"/>), it is passed the
	<option>--with-hc-pkg</option>,
	<option>--prefix</option>, <option>--bindir</option>,
	<option>--libdir</option>, <option>--datadir</option> and
	<option>--libexecdir</option> options.
	In addition the value of the <option>--with-compiler</option>
	option is passed in a <option>--with-hc</option> option  and
        all options specified with <option>--configure-option</option>=
        are passed on.</para>

      <sect3 id="setup-configure-programs">
	<title>Programs used for building</title>

	<para>The following options govern the programs used to process
	  the source files of a package:</para>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--ghc</option> or <option>-g</option></term>
	    <term><option>--nhc</option></term>
	    <term><option>--jhc</option></term>
	    <term><option>--hugs</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Specify which Haskell implementation to use to build
		the package.  At most one of these flags may be given.
		If none is given, the implementation under which the setup
		script was compiled or interpreted is used.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--with-compiler</option>=<replaceable>path</replaceable>
	    or <option>-w</option><replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Specify the path to a particular compiler.  If given,
		this must match the implementation selected above.
		The default is to search for the usual name of the
		selected implementation.</para>
	      <para>This flag also sets the default value of the
		<option>--with-hc-pkg</option> option to the package tool
		for this compiler.
		Check the output of <literal>setup configure -v</literal>
		to ensure that it finds the right package tool (or use
		<option>--with-hc-pkg</option> explicitly).</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--with-hc-pkg</option>=<replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Specify the path to the package tool, e.g.
		<command>ghc-pkg</command>.
		The package tool must be compatible with the compiler
		specified by <option>--with-compiler</option>.
		If this option is omitted, the default value is determined
		from the compiler selected.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--with-<replaceable>prog</replaceable></option>=<replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Specify the path to the program <replaceable>prog</replaceable>.
                Any program known to Cabal can be used in place of
                <replaceable>prog</replaceable>. It can either be a fully
                path or the name of a program that can be found on the program
                 search path. For example: <option>--with-ghc=ghc-6.6.1</option>
                or <option>--with-cpphs=/usr/local/bin/cpphs</option>.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-options</option>=<replaceable>options</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Specify additional options to the program <replaceable>prog</replaceable>.
                Any program known to Cabal can be used in place of
                <replaceable>prog</replaceable>. For example:
                <option>--alex-options="--template=mytemplatedir/"</option>.</para>
        <para>The <replaceable>options</replaceable> is split into program options
                based on spaces. Any options containing embeded spaced need to
                be quoted, for example
                <literal>--foo-options='--bar="C:\Program File\Bar"'</literal>. As an
                alternative that takes only one option at a time but avoids the
                need to quote, use 
                <option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-option</option> instead.
        </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-option</option>=<replaceable>option</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Specify a single additional option to the program
              <replaceable>prog</replaceable>.</para>
        <para>For passing an option that contain embeded spaces, such as a file
              name with embeded spaces, using this rather than
              <option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-options</option> means you
              do not need an additional level of quoting. Of course if
              you are using a command shell you may still need to quote, for
              example <literal>--foo-options="--bar=C:\Program File\Bar"</literal>.
        </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
  <para>All of the options passed with either
        <option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-options</option> or
        <option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-option</option> are passed
        in the order they were specified on the configure command line.
  </para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="setup-configure-paths">
	<title>Installation paths</title>

	<para>The following options govern the location of installed files
	  from a package:</para>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--prefix</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>The root of the installation. For example for a global
	      install you might use
	      <filename>/usr/local</filename> on a Unix system, or
	      <filename>C:\Program Files</filename> on a Windows system.
	      The other installation paths are usually subdirectories of
	      <replaceable>prefix</replaceable>, but they don't have
	      to be.</para>
              <para>In the simple build system, <replaceable>dir</replaceable>
                may contain the following path variables:
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--bindir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Executables that the user might invoke are installed here.</para>
              <para>In the simple build system, <replaceable>dir</replaceable>
                may contain the following path variables:
                <replaceable>$prefix</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--libdir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Object-code libraries are installed here.</para>
              <para>In the simple build system, <replaceable>dir</replaceable>
                may contain the following path variables:
                <replaceable>$prefix</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$bindir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--libexecdir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Executables that are not expected to be invoked
	      directly by the user are installed here.</para>
              <para>In the simple build system, <replaceable>dir</replaceable>
                may contain the following path variables:
                <replaceable>$prefix</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$bindir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libsubdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--datadir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Architecture-independent data files are installed
	      here.</para>
              <para>In the simple build system, <replaceable>dir</replaceable>
                may contain the following path variables:
                <replaceable>$prefix</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$bindir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libsubdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<para>In addition the simple build system supports the following
         installation path options:</para>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--libsubdir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>A subdirectory of <replaceable>libdir</replaceable>
	        in which libraries are actually installed.  For example,
	        in the simple build system on Unix, the default
	        <replaceable>libdir</replaceable> is
	        <filename>/usr/local/lib</filename>, and
	        <replaceable>libsubdir</replaceable> contains the package
	        identifier and compiler,
	        e.g. <literal>mypkg-0.2/ghc-6.4</literal>, so libraries
	        would be installed in
	        <filename>/usr/local/lib/mypkg-0.2/ghc-6.4</filename>.
              </para>
              <para><replaceable>dir</replaceable> may contain the following path
                variables:
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--datasubdir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>A subdirectory of <replaceable>datadir</replaceable>
		in which data files are actually installed.
              </para>
              <para><replaceable>dir</replaceable> may contain the following path
                variables:
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--docdir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Documentation files are installed relative to this directory.
              </para>
              <para><replaceable>dir</replaceable> may contain the following path
                variables:
                <replaceable>$prefix</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$bindir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libsubdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$datadir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$datasubdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--htmldir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>HTML documentation files are installed relative to this directory.
              </para>
              <para><replaceable>dir</replaceable> may contain the following path
                variables:
                <replaceable>$prefix</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$bindir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$libsubdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$datadir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$datasubdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$docdir</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--program-prefix</option>=<replaceable>prefix</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Prepend <replaceable>prefix</replaceable> to installed program names.
              </para>
              <para><replaceable>prefix</replaceable> may contain the following path
                variables:
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--program-suffix</option>=<replaceable>suffix</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Append <replaceable>suffix</replaceable> to installed program names. The
	      most obvious use for this is to append the program's version number to make it
	      possible to install several versions of a program at once:
	      <literal>--program-suffix='$version'</literal>.
              </para>
              <para><replaceable>suffix</replaceable> may contain the following path
                variables:
                <replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$pkg</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$version</replaceable>,
                <replaceable>$compiler</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$os</replaceable>,
		<replaceable>$arch</replaceable>
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

	<sect4 id="simple-path-vars">
	  <title>Path variables in the simple build system</title>

	  <para>For the simple build system, there are a number of variables
            that can be used when specifying installation paths. The defaults
            are also specified in terms of these variables. A number of the
            variables are actually for other paths, like
            <literal>$prefix</literal>. This allows paths to be specified
            relative to each other rather than as absolute paths, which is
            important for building relocatable packages (see
            <xref linkend="prefix-independence"/>).</para>

	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$prefix</replaceable></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The path variable that stands for the root of the
                  installation.</para>
                <para>For an installation to be relocatable, all other
                   instllation paths must be relative to the
                   <replaceable>$prefix</replaceable> variable.</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$bindir</replaceable></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The path variable that expands to the path given by
                the <option>--bindir</option> configure option (or the
                default).</para>
              </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$libdir</replaceable></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>As above but for <option>--libdir</option></para>
              </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$libsubdir</replaceable></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>As above but for <option>--libsubdir</option></para>
              </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$datadir</replaceable></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>As above but for <option>--datadir</option></para>
              </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$datasubdir</replaceable></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>As above but for <option>--datasubdir</option></para>
              </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$docdir</replaceable></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>As above but for <option>--docdir</option></para>
              </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$pkgid</replaceable></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The name and version of the package, eg
                  <literal>mypkg-0.2</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$pkg</replaceable></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The name of the package, eg
                  <literal>mypkg</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$version</replaceable></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The version of the package, eg
                  <literal>0.2</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$compiler</replaceable></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The compiler being used to build the package, eg
                  <literal>ghc-6.6.1</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$os</replaceable></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The operating system of the computer being used to build
		the package, eg <literal>linux</literal>,
		<literal>windows</literal>, <literal>osx</literal>,
		<literal>freebsd</literal> or <literal>solaris</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	    <varlistentry>
	      <term><replaceable>$arch</replaceable></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The architecture of the computer being used to build the
		package, eg <literal>i386</literal>, <literal>x86_64</literal>,
		<literal>ppc</literal> or <literal>sparc</literal></para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>

	  </variablelist>
	</sect4>

	<sect4 id="simple-paths">
	  <title>Paths in the simple build system</title>

	  <para>For the simple build system, the following defaults
	  apply:</para>

	  <informaltable>
	    <tgroup cols="3">
	      <colspec align="left"/>
	      <colspec align="left"/>
	      <colspec align="left"/>

	      <thead>
		<row>
		  <entry>Option</entry>
		  <entry>Windows Default</entry>
		  <entry>Unix Default</entry>
		</row>
	      </thead>
	      <tbody>
		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--prefix</literal> (global installs with the
		         <literal>--global</literal> flag) </entry>
		  <entry><filename>C:\Program Files\Haskell</filename></entry>
		  <entry><filename>/usr/local</filename></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--prefix</literal> (per-user installs with
		         the <literal>--user</literal> flag)</entry>
		  <entry><filename>C:\Documents And Settings\<replaceable>user</replaceable>\Application Data\cabal</filename></entry>
		  <entry><filename><replaceable>$HOME</replaceable>/.cabal</filename></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--bindir</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix\bin</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix/bin</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--libdir</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix/lib</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--libsubdir</literal> (Hugs)</entry>
		  <entry><literal>hugs\packages\$pkg</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>hugs/packages/$pkg</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--libsubdir</literal> (others)</entry>
		  <entry><literal>$pkgid\$compiler</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$pkgid/$compiler</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--libexecdir</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix\$pkgid</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix/libexec</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--datadir</literal> (executable)</entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix/share</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--datadir</literal> (library)</entry>
		  <entry><filename>C:\Program Files\Haskell</filename></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix/share</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--datasubdir</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$pkgid</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$pkgid</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--docdir</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$prefix\doc\$pkgid</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$datadir/doc/$pkgid</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--htmldir</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$docdir\html</literal></entry>
		  <entry><literal>$docdir/html</literal></entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--program-prefix</literal></entry>
		  <entry>(empty)</entry>
		  <entry>(empty)</entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry><literal>--program-suffix</literal></entry>
		  <entry>(empty)</entry>
		  <entry>(empty)</entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </informaltable>
	</sect4>

	<sect4 id="prefix-independence">
	  <title>Prefix-independence</title>

	  <para>On Windows, and when using Hugs on any system, it is
	    possible to obtain the pathname of the running program.
	    This means that we can construct an installable executable
	    package that is independent of its absolute install location.
	    The executable can find its auxiliary files by finding its
	    own path and knowing the location of the other files relative
	    to <replaceable>bindir</replaceable>.  Prefix-independence is
	    particularly useful: it means the user can choose the install
	    location (i.e. the value of <replaceable>prefix</replaceable>)
	    at install-time, rather than having to bake the path into
	    the binary when it is built.</para>

	  <para>In order to achieve this, we require
	    that for an executable on Windows, all
	    of <replaceable>bindir</replaceable>,
	    <replaceable>libdir</replaceable>,
	    <replaceable>datadir</replaceable> and
	    <replaceable>libexecdir</replaceable> begin with
	    <literal>$prefix</literal>. If this is not the case
	    then the compiled executable will have baked in
	    all absolute paths.</para>

	  <para>The application need do nothing special to achieve
	    prefix-independence.  If it finds any files using
	    <literal>getDataFileName</literal> and the other functions
	    provided for the purpose (see <xref linkend="paths-module"/>),
	    the files will be accessed relative to the location of the
	    current executable.</para>

	  <para>A library cannot (currently) be prefix-independent,
	    because it will be linked into an executable whose
	    file system location bears no relation to the library
	    package.</para>
	</sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="flag-control">
	<title>Controlling Flag Assignments</title>
	<para>Flag assignments (see <xref linkend="conditional-resolution"/>) can be
  controlled with the following	command line options.</para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>-f</option><replaceable>flagname</replaceable> or
	    <option>-f</option><literal>-</literal><replaceable>flagname</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Force the specified flag to
	      <literal>true</literal> or <literal>false</literal> (if
	      preceded with a <literal>-</literal>). Later
	      specifications for the same flags will override earlier,
	      i.e., specifying <literal>-fdebug -f-debug</literal> is
	      equivalent to <literal>-f-debug</literal></para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--flags</option>=<replaceable>flagspecs</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Same as <option>-f</option>, but allows specifying
	      multiple flag assignments at once.  The parameter is a
	      space-separated list of flag names (to force a flag to
	      <literal>true</literal>), optionally preceded by a
	      <literal>-</literal> (to force a flag to
	      <literal>false</literal>). For example,
	      <literal>--flags="debug -feature1 feature2"</literal> is
	      equivalent to <literal>-fdebug -f-feature1
	      -ffeature2</literal>.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
      </sect3>


      <sect3 id="setup-configure-misc">
	<title>Miscellaneous options</title>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--user</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Does a per-user installation. This changes the default
		installation prefix (see <xref linkend="simple-paths"/>).
		It also allow dependencies to be satisfied by the user's
		package database, in addition to the global database.</para>

	      <para>This also implies a default of <option>--user</option>
		for any subsequent <literal>install</literal> command,
		as packages registered in the global database should not
		depend on packages registered in a user's database.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--global</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Does a global installation. In this case
		package dependencies must be satisfied by the global
		package database. All packages in the user's package database
		will be ignored. Typically the final instllation step will
		require administrative privileges.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--package-db</option>=<replaceable>db</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Allows package dependencies to be satisfied from this
                additional package database <replaceable>db</replaceable> in
                addition to the global package database. All packages in the
                user's package database will be ignored. The interpretation
                of <replaceable>db</replaceable> is implementation-specific.
                Typically it will be a file or directory. Not all
                implementations support arbitrary package databases.
              </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-optimization</option>[=<replaceable>n</replaceable>] or <option>-O</option>[<replaceable>n</replaceable>]</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Build with optimization flags (if available).
		This is appropriate for production use, taking more time
		to build faster libraries and programs.</para>
	      <para>
	        The optional <replaceable>n</replaceable> value is the
		optimisation level. Some compilers support multiple
		optimisation levels. The range is 0 to 2. Level 0 is
		equivalent to <option>--disable-optimization</option>,
		level 1 is the default if no <replaceable>n</replaceable>
		parameter is given. Level 2 is higher optimisation if the
		compiler supports it. Level 2 is likely to lead to longer
		compile times and bigger generated code.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-optimization</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Build without optimization.  This is suited for
		development: building will be quicker, but the resulting
		library or programs will be slower.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-library-profiling</option> or
	      <option>-p</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Request that an additional version of the library
		with profiling features enabled be built and installed
		(only for implementations that support profiling).</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-library-profiling</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Do not generate an additional profiling
		version of the library.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-executable-profiling</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Any executables generated should have profiling enabled
		(only for implementations that support profiling).  For this
		to work, all libraries used by these executables must also
		have been built with profiling support.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-executable-profiling</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Do not enable profiling in generated
		executables.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-library-vanilla</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Build ordinary libraries (as opposed to profiling
                libraries). This is independent of the
                <option>--enable-library-profiling</option> option. If you
                enable both, you get both.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-library-vanilla</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Do not build ordinary libraries. This is useful
                in conjunction with <option>--enable-library-profiling</option>
                to build only profiling libraries, rather than profiling and
                ordinary libraries.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-library-for-ghci</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Build libraries suitable for use with GHCi.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-library-for-ghci</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Not all platforms support GHCi and indeed on some
                platforms, trying to build GHCi libs fails. In such cases
                this flag can be used as a workaround.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-split-objs</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Use the GHC <option>-split-objs</option> feature when
                building the library. This reduces the final size of the
                executables that use the library by allowing them to link with
                only the bits that they use rather than the entire library.
                The downside is that building the library takes longer and uses
                considerably more memory.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-split-objs</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Do not use the GHC <option>-split-objs</option>
                feature. This makes building the library quicker but the final
                executables that use the library will be larger.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-executable-stripping</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		(default) When installing binary executable programs, run the
		<literal>strip</literal> program on the binary. This can
		considerably reduce the size of the executable binary file. It
		does this by removing debugging information and symbols. While
		such extra information is useful for debugging C programs with
		traditional debuggers it is rarely helpful for debugging
		binaries produced by Haskell compilers.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		Not all Haskell implementations generate native binaries. For
		such implementations this option has no effect.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-executable-stripping</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Do not strip binary executables during installation. You
		might want to use this option if you need to debug a program
		using gdb, for example if you want to debug the C parts of a
		program containing both Haskell and C code. Another reason is
		if your are building a package for a system which has a policy
		of managing the stripping itself (such as some linux
		distributions).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--enable-shared</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Build shared library. This implies a seperate
	      compiler run to generate position independent code as
	      required on most platforms.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--disable-shared</option></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>(default) Do not build shared library.</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
            <term><option>--configure-option</option>=<replaceable>str</replaceable></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>An extra option to an external
                <filename>configure</filename> script,
                if one is used (see <xref linkend="system-dependent"/>).
                There can be several of these options.</para>
            </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--extra-include-dirs</option>[=<replaceable>dir</replaceable>]</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		An extra directory to search for C header files. You can use
		this flag multiple times to get a list of directories.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		You might need to use this flag if you have standard system
		header files in a non-standard location that is not mentioned
		in the package's <filename>.cabal</filename> file. Using this
		option has the same affect as appending the directory
		<replaceable>dir</replaceable> to the
		<literal>include-dirs</literal> field in each library and
		executable in the package's <filename>.cabal</filename> file.
		The advantage of course is that you do not have to modify the
		package at all. These extra directories will be used while
		building the package and for libraries it is also saved in the
		package registration information and used when compiling
		modules that use the library.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--extra-lib-dirs</option>[=<replaceable>dir</replaceable>]</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		An extra directory to search for system libraries files. You
		can use this flag multiple times to get a list of directories.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		You might need to use this flag if you have standard system
		libraries in a non-standard location that is not mentioned
		in the package's <filename>.cabal</filename> file. Using this
		option has the same affect as appending the directory
		<replaceable>dir</replaceable> to the
		<literal>extra-lib-dirs</literal> field in each library and
		executable in the package's <filename>.cabal</filename> file.
		The advantage of course is that you do not have to modify the
		package at all. These extra directories will be used while
		building the package and for libraries it is also saved in the
		package registration information and used when compiling
		modules that use the library.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

	<para>In the simple build infrastructure, an additional option
	  is recognized:</para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><option>--scratchdir</option>=<replaceable>dir</replaceable></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Specify the directory into which the Hugs output will be
		placed (default: <filename>dist/scratch</filename>).</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-build">
      <title>setup build</title>
      <para>Perform any preprocessing or compilation needed to make this
        package ready for installation.</para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
	      <varlistentry>
	        <term><option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-options</option>=<replaceable>options</replaceable></term>
	        <term><option>--<replaceable>prog</replaceable>-option</option>=<replaceable>option</replaceable></term>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>These are mostly the same as the options configure step (see
              <xref linkend="setup-configure-programs"/>). Unlike the options
              specified at the configure step, any program options specified at
              the build step are not persistent but are used for that
              invocation only. They options specified at the build step are in
              addition not in replacement of any options specified at the
              configure step.
            </para>
	        </listitem>
	      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-makefile">
      <title>setup makefile</title>
      <para>Generate a <filename>Makefile</filename> that may be used
      to compile the Haskell modules to object code.
      This command is currently only supported when building libraries,
      and only if the compiler is GHC.</para>

      <para>The makefile command replaces part of the work done by
      <literal>setup build</literal>.  The sequence of commands would
      typically be:
<programlisting>
runhaskell Setup.hs makefile
make
runhaskell Setup.hs build
</programlisting>
      where <literal>setup makefile</literal> does the preprocessing,
      <literal>make</literal> compiles the Haskell modules, and
      <literal>setup build</literal> performs any final steps, such as
      building the library archives.</para>

      <para>The Makefile does not use GHC's <literal>--make</literal>
      flag to compile the modules, instead it compiles modules one at
      a time, using dependency information generated by GHC's
      <literal>-M</literal> flag.  There are two reasons you might
      therefore want to use <literal>setup makefile</literal>:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You want to build in parallel using <literal>make -j</literal>.
          Currently, <literal>setup build</literal> on its own does not support
          building in parallel.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You want to build an individual module, pass extra
          flags to a compilation, or do other non-standard things that
          <literal>setup build</literal> does not support.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
	  <term><option>--file</option>=<replaceable>filename</replaceable> or
            <option>-f</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specify the output file (default <filename>Makefile</filename>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-haddock">
      <title>setup haddock</title>
      <para>Build the documentation for the package using &Haddock;.  By
      default, only the documentation for the exposed modules is generated
      (see <xref linkend="setup-haddock-executables"/>).</para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--hoogle</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Generate a file
            <filename>dist/doc/html/<replaceable>pkgid</replaceable>.txt</filename>,
            which can be converted by
            <ulink url="http://www.haskell.org/hoogle/">Hoogle</ulink>
            into a database for searching. This is
            equivalent to running &Haddock; with the <option>--hoogle</option> flag.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--html-location</option>=<replaceable>url</replaceable></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specify a template for the location of HTML documentation
              for prerequisite packages.  The substitutions listed in
              <xref linkend="simple-paths"/> are applied to the template
              to obtain a location for each package, which will be used
              by hyperlinks in the generated documentation.  For example,
              the following command generates links pointing at &HackageDB;
              pages:</para>
            <screen>setup haddock --html-location='http://hackage.haskell.org/packages/archive/$pkg/latest/doc/html'</screen>
            <para>Here the argument is quoted to prevent substitution
              by the shell.</para>
            <para>If this option is omitted, the location for each package
              is obtained using the package tool (e.g.
              <command>ghc-pkg</command>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="setup-haddock-executables">
          <term><option>--executables</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Also run &Haddock; for the modules of all the executable
            programs.  By default &Haddock; is run only on the exported
            modules.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="setup-haddock-internal">
          <term><option>--internal</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Run &Haddock; for the all modules, including unexposed ones, and 
            make &Haddock; generate documentation for unexported symbols
            as well.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="setup-haddock-css">
	  <term><option>--css</option>=<replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The argument <replaceable>path</replaceable> denotes a CSS
	    file, which is passed to &Haddock; and used to set the style of
	    the generated documentation. This is only needed to override the
	    default style that &Haddock; uses.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--hyperlink-source</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Generate &Haddock; documentation integrated with &HsColour;.
            First, &HsColour; is run to generate colourised code.
            Then &Haddock; is run to generate HTML documentation.  Each
            entity shown in the documentation is linked to its definition in
            the colourised code.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>--hscolour-css</option>=<replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The argument <replaceable>path</replaceable> denotes a CSS
            file, which is passed to &HsColour; as in</para>
            <screen>
runhaskell Setup.hs hscolour --css=<replaceable>path</replaceable></screen>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-hscolour">
      <title>setup hscolour</title>
      <para>Produce colourised code in HTML format using &HsColour;.
      Colourised code for exported modules is put in
      <filename>dist/doc/html/<replaceable>pkgid</replaceable>/src</filename>.</para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--executables</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Also run &HsColour; on the sources of all executable
            programs.  Colourised code is put in
            <filename>dist/doc/html/<replaceable>pkgid</replaceable>/<replaceable>executable</replaceable>/src</filename>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--css</option>=<replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Copy the CSS file from <replaceable>path</replaceable> to
            <filename>dist/doc/html/<replaceable>pkgid</replaceable>/src/hscolour.css</filename>
            for exported modules, or to
            <filename>dist/doc/html/<replaceable>pkgid</replaceable>/<replaceable>executable</replaceable>/src/hscolour.css</filename>
            for executable programs.  The CSS file defines the actual colours
            used to colourise code.  Note that the
            <filename>hscolour.css</filename> file is required for the code
            to be actually colourised.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-install">
      <title>setup install</title>
      <para>Copy the files into the install locations and (for library
        packages) register the package with the compiler, i.e. make the
        modules it contains available to programs.</para>

      <para>The install locations are determined by options to
        <command>setup configure</command>
	(see <xref linkend="setup-configure-paths"/>).</para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--global</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Register this package in the system-wide database.
	      (This is the default, unless the <option>--user</option>
	      option was supplied to the <literal>configure</literal>
	      command.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--user</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Register this package in the user's local package database.
	      (This is the default if the <option>--user</option>
	      option was supplied to the <literal>configure</literal>
	      command.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-copy">
      <title>setup copy</title>
      <para>Copy the files without registering them.  This command
        is mainly of use to those creating binary packages.</para>

      <para>This command takes the following option:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--destdir</option>=<replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specify the directory under which to place
              installed files.  If this is not given, then the root
              directory is assumed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-register">
      <title>setup register</title>
      <para>Register this package with the compiler, i.e. make the
        modules it contains available to programs.  This only makes sense
        for library packages.  Note that the <literal>install</literal>
        command incorporates this action.  The main use of this
        separate command is in the post-installation step for a binary
        package.</para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--global</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Register this package in the system-wide database.
              (This is the default.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--user</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Register this package in the user's local package
              database.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--gen-script</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Instead of registering the package, generate a script
              containing commands to perform the registration.  On Unix,
              this file is called <filename>register.sh</filename>, on
              Windows, <filename>register.bat</filename>.  This script
              might be included in a binary bundle, to be run after the
              bundle is unpacked on the target system.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--gen-pkg-config</option>=[<replaceable>path</replaceable>]</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Instead of registering the package, generate a package
              registration file. This only applies to compilers that support
              package registration files which at the moment is only GHC.
              The file should be used with the compiler's mechanism for
              registering packages.</para>
            <para>This option is mainly intended for packaging systems. If
              possible use the <option>--gen-script</option> option instead
              since it is more portable across Haskell implementations.</para>
            <para>The <replaceable>path</replaceable> is optional and can be
              used to specify a particular output file to generate. Otherwise, 
              by default the file is the package name and version with a
              <literal>.conf</literal> extension.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term><option>--inplace</option></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Registers the package for use directly from the
	    build tree, without needing to install it.  This can be
	    useful for testing: there's no need to install the package
	    after modifying it, just recompile and test.</para>

            <para>This flag does not create a build-tree-local package
            database.  It still registers the package in one of the
            user or global databases.</para>

	    <para>However, there are some caveats.  It only works with
	    GHC (currently).  It only works if your package doesn't
	    depend on having any supplemental files installed - plain
	    Haskell libraries should be fine.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-unregister">
      <title>setup unregister</title>
      <para>Deregister this package with the compiler.</para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--global</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Deregister this package in the system-wide database.
              (This is the default.)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--user</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Deregister this package in the user's local package
              database.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--gen-script</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Instead of deregistering the package, generate a script
              containing commands to perform the deregistration.  On Unix,
              this file is called <filename>unregister.sh</filename>, on
              Windows, <filename>unregister.bat</filename>.  This script
              might be included in a binary bundle, to be run on the
              target system.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-clean">
      <title>setup clean</title>
      <para>Remove any local files created during the
        <literal>configure</literal>, <literal>build</literal>,
        <literal>haddock</literal>, <literal>register</literal> or
        <literal>unregister</literal> steps, and also any files and
        directories listed in the <literal>extra-tmp-files</literal>
        field.</para>

      <para>This command takes the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--save-configure</option> or <option>-s</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Keeps the configuration information so it is not necessary
              to run the configure step again before building.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-test">
      <title>setup test</title>

      <para>Run the test suite specified by the
      <literal>runTests</literal> field of
      <literal>Distribution.Simple.UserHooks</literal>.  See &Simple;
      for information about creating hooks and using
      <literal>defaultMainWithHooks</literal>.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="setup-sdist">
      <title>setup sdist</title>
      <para>Create a system- and compiler-independent source distribution
        in a file
        <filename><replaceable>package</replaceable>-<replaceable>version</replaceable>.tar.gz</filename>
        in the <filename>dist</filename> subdirectory, for distribution
        to package builders.  When unpacked, the commands listed in this
        section will be available.</para>

      <para>The files placed in this distribution are the package
        description file, the setup script, the sources of the modules
        named in the package description file, and files named in the
        <literal>license-file</literal>, <literal>main-is</literal>,
        <literal>c-sources</literal>, <literal>data-files</literal> and
        <literal>extra-source-files</literal> fields.</para>

      <para>This command takes the following option:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--snapshot</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Append today's date
              (in <replaceable>YYYYMMDD</replaceable> form) to the version
              number for the generated source package.  The original
              package is unaffected.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bugs">
    <title>Reporting bugs and deficiencies</title>

    <para>Please report any flaws or feature requests in the
      <ulink url="http://hackage.haskell.org/trac/hackage/">bug
      tracker</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>For general discussion or queries email the libraries mailing list
    <email>libraries@haskell.org</email>. There is also a development mailing
    list <email>cabal-devel@haskell.org</email>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="stability">
    <title>Stability of Cabal interfaces</title>

    <para>The Cabal library and related infrastructure is still under active
      development. New features are being added and limitations and bugs are
      being fixed. This requires internal changes and often user visible
      changes as well. We therefor cannot promise complete future-proof
      stability, at least not without halting all development work.</para>

    <para>This section documents the aspects of the Cabal interface that we can
      promise to keep stable and which bits are subject to change.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Cabal file format</title>
      <para>
        This is backwards compatible and mostly forwards compatible.
        New fields can be added without breaking older versions of Cabal.
        Fields can be deprecated without breaking older packages.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Command-line interface</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Very Stable Command-line interfaces</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              ./setup configure
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>--prefix</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>--user</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>--ghc, --hugs</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>--verbose</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>--prefix</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>./setup build</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>./setup install</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>./setup register</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>./setup copy</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Stable Command-line interfaces</title>
	<para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Unstable command-line</title>
	<para></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Functions and Types</title>
      <para>
        The Cabal library follows the <ulink
        url="http://haskell.org/haskellwiki/Package_versioning_policy">Package
        Versioning Policy</ulink>. This means that within a stable major
        release, for example 1.2.x, there will be no incompatible API changes.
        But minor versions increments, for example 1.2.3, indicate compatible
        API additions.
      </para>

      <para>
        The Package Versioning Policy does not require any API guarantees
        between major releases, for example between 1.2.x and 1.4.x. In
        practise of course not everything changes between major releases. Some
        parts of the API are more prone to change than others. The rest of this
        section gives some informal advice on what level of API stability you
        can expect between major releases.
      </para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Very Stable API</title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><literal>defaultMain</literal></para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <literal>defaultMainWithHooks defaultUserHooks</literal>
            </para>
            <para>
              But regular <literal>defaultMainWithHooks</literal> isn't stable
              since <literal>UserHooks</literal> changes.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Semi-stable API</title>
        <para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><literal>UserHooks</literal> The hooks API will change in the
              future</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><literal>Distribution.<replaceable>*</replaceable></literal>
              is mostly declarative information about packages and is somewhat
              stable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Unstable API</title>
        <para>
          Everything under
          <literal>Distribution.Simple.<replaceable>*</replaceable></literal>
          has no stability guarantee.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Hackage</title>
      <para>
        The index format is a partly stable interface. It consists of a tar.gz
        file that contains directories with <filename>.cabal</filename> files
        in. In future it may contain more kinds of files so do not assume every
        file is a <filename>.cabal</filename> file. Incompatible revisions to
        the format would involve bumping the name of the index file, i.e.,
        <filename>00-index.tar.gz</filename>,
        <filename>01-index.tar.gz</filename> etc.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</article>
